Guide to Culinary Ephemera: Flour Products, Leavening Agents, and Baked Goods ams.0058
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
Culinary Ephemera: Flour Products, Leavening Agents, and Baked Goods
1864-2002
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
ams.0058
17.5 Linear Feet 35 small manuscript boxes
Forms part of the Janice Bluestein Longone Culinary Archive. This collection includes promotional materials relating to flour (primarily wheat flour); leavening agents such as yeast, baking powder, and baking soda; and some material focused generally on baked goods. Publications date from 1864-2002, with most materials dating from after 1900.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Acquisitions
Box 37 ACQ: 35669; 35823. Box 38 ACQ: 35669; 35992; 36668; P 2269. Box 39 ACQ: 35669; 35823; 36698-D; 36698-G. Box 40 ACQ: 35669, 35823. Box 41 ACQ: 35669; Janice B. Longone; Gift; 6/21/2001. Box 42 ACQ: 35669; Janice B. Longone; Gift; 6/21/2001. Box 43 ACQ: 35669, 35823. Box 44 ACQ: 35669; 35823. Box 45 ACQ: 35669; 35823. Box 46 ACQ: 35669; 35823. Box 47 ACQ: 35669; Janice B. Longone; Gift; 6/21/2001. Box 48 ACQ: 35669. Box 49 ACQ: 35669; 35823; 35992. Box 139 ACQ: 35669; 37295; 35992; 36450; 35547-B. Box 140 ACQ: 35669; 35823. Box 141 ACQ: 35669; P. 2001; 2104; P. 2358. Box 142 ACQ: 35669; 35823; 35992; 36668; P. 2399.2. Box 144 ACQ: 37042; 35992; 35669; p2447.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into three series, based on subject and physical organization. These series are: Series 1: Flour Products, Series 2: Leavening Agents, and Series 3: Flour, Baking Powder, and Baked Goods. Series 3 contains a mix of subjects, due to previously-established physical arrangement of the collection.
Custodial History
The Janice Bluestein Longone Culinary Archive (JBLCA) transferred from the William L. Clements Library in June 2013.
Scope and Contents
Forms part of the Janice Bluestein Longone Culinary Archive. This collection includes promotional materials relating to flour (primarily wheat flour); leavening agents such as yeast, baking powder, and baking soda; and some material focused generally on baked goods. Publications date from 1864-2002, with most materials dating from after 1900.
Janice Bluestein Longone Culinary Archive.; Culinary ephemera (Promotional).; Cooking.; Baking powder.; Baking.; Home economics.; Biscuits.; Sodium bicarbonate.; Yeast.; Cooking (Bread).; Bread.; Crackers.; Desserts.; Cake.; Sandwiches.; Bagels.; Breading.; Icings Cake.; Edible coatings.; Cookies.; Stuffing (Cooking).; Pies.; Icings (Confectionery).; Flour mills.; Cooking--Study and teaching.; Pastry.
- Flour Products
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1: Flour includes publications from a range of companies promoting flour products. Most publications focus on recipes for sweet baked goods, such as cake, pie, quickbreads, and cookies, but some provide recipes for sandwiches or other savory dishes. Although the inclusive dates are 1869-2002, most publications date from the 1910s-1970s. In addition to numerous flour companies, including Robin Hood Flour Mills, Washburn Crosby Company, and King Arthur Flour, among others, this series includes publications from corporations that produced both flour and baking mixes, such as various iterations of the Pillsbury company.
  - Box 8a.
    Creators include:
    Anderson, Martha Lee.
    Fuertes, Louis Agassiz, 1874-1927.
    Beeks, Henrietta C.
    Hill, Janet McKenzie, 1852-1933.
    Calumet Baking Powder Company.
    General Food Sales Co.
    Church & Dwight Co.
    Rumford Chemical Works.
    Rumford Company.
    Hulman and Company (Terre Haute, Ind.)
    Jaques Mfg. Co.
    R.B. Davis Company.
    Price Baking Powder Co.
    Royal Baking Powder Company.
    - Reliable recipes. 23rd ed. 80 p., circa 1920s (Box 8a, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes Calumet Baking Powder. Includes color illustrations of woman in period dress, company child and dog mascots, company model kitchen and laboratories, facilities, product packaging, and serving suggestions; product quality guarantee; Modern Priscilla certificate of approval; offers for additional copies of publication and The children's party book; full page advertisements for product and for company-sponsored radio programs; descriptions of product composition and of the company's Home Economics Dept.; table of cooking times; table of ideal food combinations; table of weights and measures; method for testing freshness of product; household hints and table etiquette; recipes for baked goods, candies, soups, salads and entrees; and index. Sample recipes: cream puffs, Charlotte Russe, and Calumet meat pie.
    - [Calumet recipe book]. 40 p., circa 1920s (Box 8a, Folder 2)
      Item [2] promotes Calumet Baking Powder. Includes menus and recipes organized by event or theme such as Afternoon Tea or Lincoln's Birthday Party; novel serving ideas; illustrations of serving suggestions, table settings and people in period dress; and index. Sample recipes: chicken mousse, Washington pie, and roast goose. Damaged: covers missing, first and last pages loose.
    - [Six Calumet Baking Powder recipe cards]., circa 1930s (Box 8a, Folder 3)
      Item [3] promotes Calumet Baking Powder. Includes six quantity recipes for cookies, quick breads, and muffins; General Foods product list; and place to record costs on each card. Sample recipe: rich corn bread. Marked: 1068-39, 1068-46, 1068-50, 1068-51, 1068-59, and 1068-192.
    - Good things to eat. 114th ed. 32 p., 1936 (Box 8a, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Arm & Hammer and Cow Brand Baking Sodas and features recipes tested and approved in the Arm & Hammer and Cow Brand Baking Soda Kitchen by Martha Lee Anderson. Includes introduction, comments on use of sour milk, buttermilk and baking soda; substitutes for sour milk and buttermilk; facts regarding plain white flour; baking and kitchen tips; tables of weights and measures, temperatures and baking times, and cooking times for vegetables; illustrations of product packaging and serving suggestions; recipes for hot breads, cakes, cookies, puddings and doughnuts, and frostings and sauces; and index. Sample recipes: bran muffins, golden spice cake, and Saturday's pudding. Marked: F-1000-1-36.
    - Arm and Hammer book of valuable recipes. 32 p., 1900 (Box 8a, Folder 5)
      Item [5] promotes Arm and Hammer baking soda. Includes introduction; comments on use of sour milk or buttermilk in place of baking powder; advantages of Arm and Hammer soda; general directions for cooking with baking soda; hints on baking; tables of weights and measures and weights per bushel of grain in 33 states; tips for using baking soda for cleaning and stain removal; what to do in case of accidents; postage rates; illustrations of people in period dress; recipes (some attributed) for soups, breads, cakes, cookies, candies, frostings, pastry, puddings, desserts, soups, and sauces; offer for additional copies; and index. Sample recipes: mock bisque soup, griddle cakes, and jelly roulade. Damaged: missing outside covers.
    - Good things to eat. 118th ed. 15 p., 1937 (Box 8a, Folder 6)
      Item [6] promotes Arm & Hammer and Cow Brand Baking Soda with introduction by Martha Lee Anderson of the Church & Dwight Co., Inc. Research Test Kitchen. Includes tips for using baking soda for cleaning, fire extinguishing and odor removal; illustrations of product packaging and serving suggestions; and recipes for cakes, frostings, cookies, and quick breads. Sample recipes: red devil's loaf cake, peanut butter icebox cookies, and lemon clover rolls. Marked: D-2000-3-37.
    - Cow Brand Soda cook book and facts worth knowing. 32 p., 1913 (Box 8a, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes Cow Brand Soda. Includes perpetual calendar; introduction to the housewife; full-page advertisement for Cow Brand Soda (or saleratus); advantages of Cow Brand Soda; use of soda with sour milk, buttermilk or cream of tartar; household tips; tips for estimating measures, measuring cubic contents of a corn crib, and capacities of square and circular cisterns; advice on using baking soda for various household tasks and for farm animals; postage rates and regulations; tables of weights and measures and weights of a bushel of grain in 34 states; how deep to plant corn and amount of barbed wire required for fence; daily savings at compound interest; illustrations of product packaging; recipes for breads, cakes, candies, desserts, puddings, pies, soups, and sauces; and index. Sample recipes: corn dodgers, Queen Ann apple flamri, and Everton taffy. Marked: (Cow).
    - [Thirty promotional cards showing useful birds of America]., circa 1920s (Box 8a, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes use of Arm & Hammer and Cow Brand Baking Sodas as a dentifrice and features commissioned illustrations of birds by Louis Agassiz Fuertes from the ninth and tenth series of "Useful birds of America". Includes common name, scientific name, and habitat information for each bird. No recipes. Each card numbered by series.
    - Eighty years of baking powder history: 1859-1939. 23 p. (Box 8a, Folder 9)
      Item [9] is a history of the Rumford Chemical Works. Includes history of the company; biographies of founders Eben N. Horseford and George F. Wilson and of Benjamin Thompson, Count Rumford; illustrated descriptions of past and present company facilities and baking powder manufacturing techniques; and quotations from the works of Count Rumford. No recipes.
    - 64 new uses for Rumford all-phosphate baking powder in daily cooking. 29 p., 1931 (Box 8a, Folder 10)
      Item [10] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Includes introduction about cooking with baking powder; advantages of Rumford all-phosphate baking powder; illustrations of product packaging, people in period dress and serving suggestions; recipes for vegetables, meat, fish, cheese, eggs, desserts, icings, and candy; and index. Sample recipes: tomato bisque, French meat sandwich, and lemon pie filling. Marked: K-104. I-31.
    - [Rumford Baking Powder notebook]. 1 v. (unpaged), circa 1800s (Box 8a, Folder 11)
      Item [11] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Notebook with blank graph-paper pages and covers with advertisements for Rumford Baking Powder. Includes product packaging illustration. Marked: A.62. Damaged: covers loose.
    - [Rumford Baking Powder cook book]. 32 p., 1909 (Box 8a, Folder 12)
      Item [12] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Includes recipes compiled by Henrietta C. Beeks for biscuits, breads, muffins, cakes, cake icings and fillings, puddings, confectionary, and ice cream; table of weights and measures; tips on measuring; offer of "Rumford complete cook book" by Lily Haxworth Wallace for 10 cards from one-pound Rumford Baking Powder cans; advice on reading the label; and illustrations of child on front cover, Rumford factory, and product packaging. Sample recipes: steamed Boston brown bread, Rumford marigold cake, and cream tutti-frutti. Name handwritten on front cover. Marked: P-49.
    - Clabber Girl baking book. 15 p., circa 1930s (Box 8a, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes Clabber Girl Baking Powder. Includes anonymous testimonials; comments on origin of baking; illustrated table of 7 vitamins and their sources; tips for perfect baking results; recipes for biscuits, muffins, quick breads, cakes, cookies, cake frostings, pastries, desserts, noodles, and dumplings; and illustrations of standard beef cuts, women in period dress, product packaging, and serving suggestions. Sample recipes: Clabber Girl biscuits, orange nut bread, and pumpkin chiffon pie.
    - The cook's book. 47 p., 1926 (Box 8a, Folder 14)
      Item [14] promotes K C Baking Powder. Includes recipes, some by Janet McKenzie Hill, for self-rising flour, breads, cakes, muffins, biscuits, pancakes, puddings, desserts, and cookies; qualities of K C Baking Powder; facsimile of award given to company for service during First World War; product guarantee; tips on oven temperature regulation; tables of proportions and equivalent weights and measures; and illustrations of company laboratory, serving suggestions, and product packaging. Sample recipes: K C German coffee cake, K C berry puffs, and K C oatmeal macaroons.
    - A lesson plan on the baking powder biscuit and its relatives (biscuits and pastries). Revised. 18 p., 1931 (Box 8a, Folder 15)
      Item [15], by Elsie Stark, director of Home economics dept., R.B. Davis Company, promotes Davis Baking Powder, Davis Dry Yeast Baking Powder, and Cocomalt. Includes classifications of batters and doughs; characteristics of the pastry group; method of mixing and essential ingredients of biscuit or pastry dough; descriptions off members of the pastry family; standard biscuit recipe; table showing relationship of certain pastry doughs; general directions for pastry; physics of pastry making; pie crust recipe; puff paste recipe; recipes for baking powder biscuits, pies, and vol-au-vents; and list of other booklets in the series. Sample recipes: bran biscuits, lemon pie, and chicken à la king vol-au-vents. Marked: A.
    - A lesson plan on deep fat frying. Revised. 19 p., 1931 (Box 8a, Folder 16)
      Item [16], produced by R.B. Davis' Home economics dept., promotes Davis Baking Powder, Davis Dry Yeast Baking Powder, and Cocomalt. Includes table of smoking temperatures of common fats; classification of fats; list of equipment for deep fat frying; list of foods that may be cooked in deep fat; temperatures and time table for deep fat frying; recipes for doughnuts, crullers, fritters, and croquettes and list of other booklets in series. Sample recipes: vanilla and mace doughnuts, corn fritters, and potato balls. Marked: C.
    - A lesson plan on baking powder batters and doughs. Revised. 10 p., 1931 (Box 8a, Folder 17)
      Item [17], produced by R.B. Davis' Home economics dept., promotes Davis Baking Powder, Davis Dry Yeast Baking Powder, and Cocomalt. Includes history of bread; notes on physics and chemistry of bread; definition of baking powder; general rules for making quick breads; general proportions for batters and doughs; recipes using batters and doughs; and list of other booklets in the series. Sample recipes: popovers, waffles, and shortcake. Marked: G.
    - Cream Baking Powder pastry book. 24 p., circa 1895 (Box 8a, Folder 18)
      Item [18] promotes Cream Baking Powder. Includes testimonial from chief steward at Young's Hotel, Boston, Mass.; Cost comparison with Royal and Cleveland baking powders; recipes for biscuits, breads, rolls, cakes, frostings, gems, muffins, griddle cakes, waffles, pies, puddings, and pudding sauces; table of weights and measures; and product packaging illustration. Sample recipes: Vienna rolls, bride's cake, and Christmas pudding. Damaged: name of owner hand written on cover.
    - Making biscuits: delicious recipes, biscuits, muffins, quick breads. 14 p., 1927 (Box 8a, Folder 19)
      Item [19] promotes Royal Baking Powder. Includes tips on making biscuits; recipes for biscuits, breads, and muffins; menus for Sunday night suppers; offer of "Royal cook book" (item [20]); and product packaging illustration. Sample recipes: Virginia biscuit, poppy muffins, and peanut butter bread.
  - Box 8b.
    Best, Nancy.
    Wessling, Hannah L.
    National Biscuit Company.
    Wheat Flour Institute.
    Fleischmann Company.
    Northwestern Yeast Company.
    American Institute of Baking.
    Pepperidge Farm, inc.
    Nabisco, Inc.
    - Royal cook book. 49 p., 1928 (Box 8b, Folder 20)
      Item [20] promotes Royal Baking Powder. Includes notes on superiority of cream of tartar baking powder; advice on measuring ingredients and baking; table of equivalent weights and measures; recipes for breads, rolls, griddle cakes, waffles, fritters, cakes, icings, puddings and other desserts, pastries, pies, soups, fish, meats, poultry, sauces, eggs, vegetables, beverages, and candy; advice on fireless cookery, cooking for an invalid, and preserving and canning; product packaging and serving suggestion illustrations; and index. Sample recipes: corn and rice pone, honey drop cakes, and stew with dumplings.
    - Wabash Baking Powder Company. 19 p., circa 1900s (Box 8b, Folder 21)
      Item [21] promotes Wabash baking powder, corn starch, soda, and lemon extract, which can be given private labels. Addressed to grocers, includes illustrations of suggested individualized packaging with pricing for various sizes and quantities and factory illustration. No recipes.
    - Winter menu magic. 24 p., 1933 (Box 8b, Folder 22)
      Item [22] promotes Uneeda Bakers crackers and cookies. Includes foreword by Nancy Best including offer to send copies of booklet; menus and recipes for variety of occasions; and index listing recipes under Uneeda product used in recipe. Sample recipes: baked meat croquettes, cranberry pie, and poularde Marie Antoinette.
    - The trick of yeast rolls and coffee cakes. 13 p., 1961 (Box 8b, Folder 23)
      Item [23] promotes yeast cooking. Designed to accompany a film strip with the same title and narration guide, includes basic sweet yeast dough recipe, further recipes for rolls and cakes, and period dress illustration. Sample recipes: hot cross buns, orange rosette coffee cake, and Stollen.
    - Easy drawing for little ones. 1 v. (unpaged), circa 1900 (Box 8b, Folder 24)
      Item [24] promotes Fleischmann's Compressed Yeast. Includes illustrated poem about girl baking bread made with Fleischmann's yeast when her mother is out shopping. No recipes. Marked: no. 18. Damaged: covers and pages loose.
    - Excellent recipes for baking with Fleischmann's Yeast. 52 p., 1910 (Box 8b, Folder 25)
      Item [25] promotes Fleischmann's Yeast. Includes suggestions for using Fleischmann's Yeast; general hints; recipes for breads, rolls, muffins, waffles, griddle cakes, and cakes; and cover illustration of girl in Dutch national costume. Sample recipes: milk bread, English muffins, and savarin. Form no. 481, D-E. 2 copies.
    - Oven melodies using Maca, the new fast granular yeast. 17 p., 1940 (Box 8b, Folder 26)
      Item [26] promotes Maca Yeast. Includes recipes for breads, rolls, coffee cakes, and root beer; offers for stamp collection stamp album and booklets about stamps; address of Hannah L. Wessling to whom questions about Maca Yeast may be sent; illustrations of period dress, serving suggestions, and product packaging; and index. Sample recipes: prune bread, 60-minute Parker House rolls, and Scandinavian Christmas bread. Damaged: cover torn.
    - Tried and tested recipes using Maca, the new fast dry yeast. 17 p., 1939 (Box 8b, Folder 27)
      Item [27] promotes Maca Yeast. Similar content to that of item [26] but without stamp-related offers and with invitation to Maca Exhibit in Food Building at 1939 New York World's Fair.
    - The art of making bread at home. 34 p., circa 1930s (Box 8b, Folder 28)
      Item [28] promotes Maca Yeast. Includes comments on ingredients and procedure used for bread making; illustrated step-by-step guide to making good bread; recipes for breads, cakes, rolls, and root beer; illustrations of Hannah L. Wessling of Home economics dept at Northwestern Yeast Co., serving suggestions, and product packaging; and index. Sample recipes: rye bread sponge method, easy graham bread, and devil's food cake.
    - Betty Arnold recipes. 16 p., circa 1950s (Box 8b, Folder 29)
      Item [29] promotes Arnold's bread and cookies. Includes image of and foreword by Betty Arnold; menus for lunch, tea, cocktail, barbecue, supper, and snack time with recipes for selected items; history of company; illustrations of kitchen, product packaging, and serving suggestions; and index. Sample recipes: buttercup cases with creamed shrimp, curried lambburger, and orange sweet toast.
    - Bread stuffing the year 'round. 1 v. (unpaged), 1950 (Box 8b, Folder 30)
      Item [30] promotes bread stuffing. Includes tips on stuffings; recipes for poultry, meat, fish, and vegetable stuffings; and serving suggestion illustration. Stamped on back cover "Compliments of Schaible's Bakery, Easton, Pa.". Sample recipes: apple-raisin bread stuffing for duck, savory stuffed baked pork chops, and Danish stuffed cabbage.
    - The fascinating story of the pretzel with "fun food" recipes. 11 p., circa 1961 (Box 8b, Folder 31)
      Item [31] promotes pretzels. Includes history of the pretzel; suggestions for serving pretzels around the clock; recipes for pretzel dippers, pretzel crumb pies, meat loaf, turkey stuffing, salads, and soup; and illustrations of 15th century pretzel bakery, coat of arms including pretzel, period dress, and serving suggestions. Sample recipes: Acapulco dip, pretzel-chocolate ice cream pie, and Pennsylvania pretzel soup.
    - Serve a surprise! 16 p., circa 1970s (Box 8b, Folder 32)
      Item [32] promotes Sara Lee frozen baked goods. Includes history of Kitchens of Sara Lee; recipes for family fare, toys, dessert parties, and important occasions; list of categories of Sara Lee baked and frozen products; suggestions for serving Sara Lee products; and serving suggestion illustrations. Some recipes include liquor as an ingredient. Sample recipes: banana split cake, frosted toy house, and mocha rum torte.
    - How to make the 10 best sandwiches of the year: [folded brochure]., 1962 (Box 8b, Folder 33)
      Item [33] promotes sandwiches. Includes 10 best sandwich recipes (attributed and illustrated) in the National Sandwich Idea Contest run jointly by the Wheat Flour Institute and the National Restaurant Association from submissions by those who work in restaurants. Sample recipes: banana ham nutwich and the pearadise crab. Marked: L-27.
    - Pepperidge Farm, "the versatile stuffing". 27 p., circa 1980s (Box 8b, Folder 34)
      Item [34] promotes Pepperidge Farm stuffings for a variety of everyday and company occasions. Includes tips on using stuffing; recipes for stuffings; notes on stuffing turkey; illustrations of serving suggestions and product packaging; and index. Sample recipes: meat loaf Italiano, dill stuffed sea bass, and stuffed artichokes. Marked: 1805.
    - Delicious dip recipes from Mr. Phipps Pretzel Chips. 32 p., 1991 (Box 8b, Folder 35)
      Item [35] promotes Mr. Phipps Pretzel Chips. Includes dip recipes (suitable for cutting out as recipe cards); coupons for Mr. Phipps Pretzel Chips, Grey Poupon mustard, Ortega salsa or sauce, Egg Beaters, Fleischmann's Margarine, and American Classic crackers; serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations; and index. Sample recipes: country mustard dip, shrimp cocktail dip, and savory broccoli dip.
    - "Better than home baked": [folded brochure]., 1991 (Box 8b, Folder 36)
      Item [36] is a catalog for Well-Bred Loaf's baked goods. Includes list of products with prices and shipping costs; details of how to order by mail or telephone; suggestions of occasions for using products; and history of company. No recipes.
    - Duncan Hines recipes & more. 32 p., 1991 (Box 8b, Folder 37)
      Item [37] promotes Duncan Hines mixes for baked goods. Includes recipes for bake sales, fall tailgate party, soccer ball cake, and kids; advice on utensils for making desserts; recipes from readers; answers to baking questions from Gwen Brima, director of Duncan Hines Kitchen; Duncan Hines coupons; pull-out recipe cards; and serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations. Sample recipes: fancy walnut brownies, autumn gold pumpkin cake, and Thanksgiving cranberry cobbler. Damaged: coupons removed.
  - Box 9.
    Howe, Eleanor.
    Crocker, Betty.
    Farmer, Fannie Merritt, 1857-1915.
    Neff, Isabel Howard.
    Garrett, Myra Russell.
    Ames, Mary Ellis.
    Pillsbury, Ann.
    Fossum, Christine.
    Swezy, Isabelle Clark.
    Baker, Margaret B.
    Nokes, Mildred Marie.
    Larsen, Margaret S.
    Kendall, Blanche Keller.